A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, International Affairs records FA748
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, International Affairs records
1950-1983
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA748
9.6 Cubic Feet 8 boxes.
8 boxes.
Biographical/Historical note
The International Affairs Department was part of the International Division of the Ford Foundation from the 1950’s until the mid-1980’s. A main focus of the department was to strengthen cultural, economic, and political ties between countries. It did this through organizing seminars and conferences on international issues, and awarding grants for research and action in various countries in need. The department supported scientific and scholarly exchanges with various countries and opened several international offices, including the Paris Office, to facilitate communication and programming overseas.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Scope and Contents
Contains records documenting: administration, the Paris office, grants, arms control, exchanges and conferences.
Arrangement
Arranged in 6 series: Series I: Administrative papers. Series II: Paris Office. Series III: Grants. Series IV: Arms Control. Series V: Exchanges. Series VI: Conferences.
Biographical / Historical
Segment One: International Activities of the Ford Foundation: An Overview
The Foundation's aspiration to become a national and international philanthropy for the advancement of human welfare was first formally expressed in the seminal 1949 report of the Gaither Study Committee, Report of the Study for the Ford Foundation on Policy and Program (RAC Library, call letters 361.7 GAI ), which was commissioned by the Board of Trustees to chart the Foundation’s future. Foundation Trustees launched Ford’s international grantmaking activities in 1950 when they approved the committee’s report and its embrace of peace, democracy, and freedom. Since then, the Foundation has tackled these goals using a variety of strategies and responding to changing contexts, from the Cold War to the 1989 fall of the Berlin Wall and beyond.
Toward the Foundation’s aspiration‎al goal, "the establishment of peace", its international activities have comprised a wide range of conceptual approaches and focus areas. These include international affairs, international studies, international understanding, arms control and disarmament, international law, international economic concerns, and overseas development in nearly every region of the world. Three distinct periods emerge for the international grantmaking defined by external contextual changes and internal changes in Foundation leadership and structures: the expansion era of 1950-1965; the transition and restructuring years of 1966-1988; and the post-1989 shift away from Cold War dichotomies. During each of the distinct historical periods the consistent objectives were: 1) to ensure freedom and democracy in developed countries; 2) to foster education and international understanding in all countries; and 3) to contribute to the social, economic, and political development of less developed countries.
- Administrative Papers, 1955-1983; I
  Scope and Contents note
  The administrative records contain general memoranda, policy and directives notes, early project planning, reviews and evaluations of ongoing projects, financial documents (including appropriations reports), procedures, and questionnaires. It also includes the files of some staff members, including Craufurd Goodwin and Richard Catalano, which contain correspondence, reports, memoranda, and meeting notes.
  - Appropriations reports, 1972-1975 (Box 1)
  - Catalano Files - Advisory directives, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Catalano Files - Budget requests, 1967 (Box 1)
  - Catalano Files - East, West, and China reports, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Catalano Files - Europe-Atlantic cooperation - reports, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Catalano Files - Grants - active, 1967 (Box 1)
  - Catalano Files - Grants - anticipated renewals, 1967 (Box 1)
  - Catalano Files - Grants - Institutional Development and Exchanges, 1967 (Box 1)
  - Catalano Files - Grants - Latin America, 1967 (Box 1)
  - Catalano Files - Internal operations - reports and evaluations, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Catalano Files - Law, international, 1965-1967 (Box 1)
  - Catalano Files - Law organizations, 1965 (Box 1)
  - Catalano Files - Law, pending projects, 1965 (Box 1)
  - Catalano Files - Law proposals, 1963-1969 (Box 1)
  - Catalano Files - Law, restrictive trade practices, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Catalano Files - Office of International Relations - files transferred, 1967 (Box 1)
  - Catalano Files - Pacific regions - reports, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Catalano Files - Policy papers, 1965-1967 (Box 1)
  - Catalano Files - Projects, pending, 1967 (Box 1)
  - Catalano Files - Proposals - British Universities, 1967 (Box 1)
  - Catalano Files - Science, general, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Catalano Files - Science policy, Europe, undated (Box 1)
  - Catalano Files - Science projects, ideas, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Catalano Files - Technology papers, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Catalano Files - U.N. Commission on International Trade Law, 1966-1967 (Box 1)
  - Catalano Files - U.S. World affairs and American Studies - reports, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Catalano Files - World Cooperation and International Order - reports, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Committee on Citizen Education in World Affairs - background information, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Committee on Citizen Education in World Affairs - consultants, 1964-1965 (Box 1)
  - Committee on Citizen Education in World Affairs - proposals and appropriations, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Country research papers, 1967 (Box 1)
  - East and West Europe review, 1967 (Box 1)
  - Financial documents and memoranda, "important", 1968-1969 (Box 1)
  - General administrative files, 1965-1968 (Box 1)
  - Goodwin Files - Affirmative action, 1974-1975 (Box 1)
  - Goodwin Files - Bader, William, 1970-1972 (Box 1)
  - Goodwin Files - Bell, David, 1970-1971 (Box 1)
  - Goodwin Files - Bell, David, 1972-1973 (Box 1)
  - Goodwin Files - Bellagio conference (COATS), 1977 (Box 1)
  - Goodwin Files - Branson, William, 1973-1974 (Box 1)
  - Goodwin Files - Budgets, 1973 (Box 2)
  - Goodwin Files - Budgets, 1973-1978 (Box 2)
  - Goodwin Files - Bundy, McGeorge, 1971-1978 (Box 2)
  - Goodwin Files - Chronological files (miscellaneous), 1977-1978 (Box 2)
  - Goodwin Files - Comparitive systems, 1973 (Box 2)
  - Goodwin Files - Education correspondence - Howe, Meane, Ward, 1971-1975 (Box 2)
  - Goodwin Files - Education in Europe, management, 1969 (Box 2)
  - Goodwin Files - Gordon, S.T., 1970-1971 (Box 2)
  - Goodwin Files - Grants, research procedures, 1971 (Box 2)
  - Goodwin Files - Grants - Employee standards for grantees, 1972 (Box 2)
  - Goodwin Files - Grants, summaries, 1969 (Box 2)
  - Goodwin Files - International Division conference, 1971 (Box 2)
  - Goodwin Files - International peace, security, and arms control, 1983 (Box 2)
  - Goodwin Files - International subcommittees, 1967-1969 (Box 2)
  - Goodwin Files - London trip with Kennedy, 1972 (Box 2)
  - Goodwin Files - Memoranda, 1972-1976 (Box 2)
  - Goodwin Files - Pending files, 1978 (Box 2)
  - Goodwin Files - Programs, future planning, 1976 (Box 2)
  - Goodwin Files - Program related investments, 1972 (Box 2)
  - Goodwin Files - Projects and travel, 1975-1977 (Box 2)
  - Goodwin Files - Public management, 1972 (Box 2)
  - Goodwin Files - Race and ethnicity, 1977-1979 (Box 2)
  - Goodwin Files - Resource bases, 1971 (Box 2)
  - Goodwin Files - Russia and Poland trip, 1971 (Box 2)
  - Goodwin Files - Silj, A., 1971-1973 (Box 2)
  - Goodwin Files - Social Science paper, responses, 1976 (Box 2)
  - Goodwin Files - Sutton, F.X., 1979-1980 (Box 2)
  - Goodwin Files - Tax laws, 1972-1974 (Box 3)
  - Goodwin Files - Technological innovation - Kahn, "The Next 33 Years: a Framework for Speculation", 1967 (Box 3)
  - Goodwin Files - U Thant correspondence, 1971-1972 (Box 3)
  - International studies - reports, mailing list, 1976-1977 (Box 3)
  - Policy directives, 1957 (Box 3)
  - Programs - American studies, 1965 (Box 3)
  - Programs - Cultural Affairs, 1957-1962 (Box 3)
  - Programs - important memoranda, 1959-1966 (Box 3)
  - Programs - Language, proposal, 1978 (Box 3)
  - Programs - Smaller European countries, 1965-1966 (Box 3)
  - Programs - Trustees future planning, 1976 (Box 3)
  - Programs - War, Peace, and Cooperation Among Nations, proposals, 1976 (Box 3)
  - Public opinion and international affairs, 1957-1968 (Box 3)
  - Self study, Office of International Relations, 1966-1969 (Box 3)
  - Status reports - Appropriations, 1969-1978 (Box 3)
  - Strategy paper - Office of International Relations, 1966 (Box 3)
  - University International support, 1968-1970 (Box 3)
- Paris Office, 1960-1976; II
  The Paris Office was open from 1970 until 1975. Its primary functions were to provide a European base for the International Affairs Department and to perform liaison services for other offices. William Bader ran the office with assistance from Marion Bieber. The files contain memoranda about policy and procedures between the Paris Office and various other offices, including New York. They also contain annual reports, circulars from Paris and other European foundations, and minutes from the European Luncheon Club, which was a periodic meeting where projects were discussed.
  - Bieber Files - Financial arrangements for closing, 1974-1976 (Box 3)
  - Bieber Files - Goodwin correspondence, 1975-1976 (Box 3)
  - Bieber, Marion and Bader, William - general memoranda, 1972 (Box 3)
  - Bieber, Marion and Goodwin - general memoranda, 1973-1976 (Box 3)
  - Bieber, Marion and Silj - general memoranda, 1972-1973 (Box 3)
  - Closure of Paris Office - memoranda, 1974-1975 (Box 3)
  - Communications coordination - Athens, Spain, 1960-1971 (Box 3)
  - Conferences, seminars, meetings, 1973-1974 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence protocols between NY and Paris offices, 1970-1971 (Box 3)
  - Development of European office, 1967-1971 (Box 3)
  - European Luncheon club, 1970 (Box 3)
  - European Luncheon Club, 1970-1973 (Box 4)
  - Goodwin files - general memoranda, 1970-1973 (Box 4)
  - Goodwin files - general memoranda, 1971 (Box 4)
  - Information circulars - outgoing, 1971-1972 (Box 4)
  - Information circulars - outgoing, 1972-1973 (Box 4)
  - International studies - Europe, memoranda, 1974-1975 (Box 4)
  - Lease for Paris Office, 1970-1972 (Box 4)
  - Lease for Reid Hall - memoranda, 1975-1976 (Box 4)
  - Local consultants - memoranda, 1972 (Box 4)
  - Memoranda - general, 1970 (Box 4)
  - Memoranda - general, 1973 (Box 4)
  - Memoranda - general, 1976 (Box 4)
  - Opening of the Paris Office, 1970 (Box 4)
- Grants, 1950-1981; III
  The International Affairs Department awarded grants for programs of world-wide scope, including education, exchanges, and aid in Atlantic and European countries and Pacific and East Asian regions. Grants also supported research and projects in East-West relations, and US foreign policy and understanding. The grants ranged from a few thousand to a few million dollars. These records consist of applications, proposals, evaluations, reports and all other supporting documents pertaining to the International Affairs grant program. Included are grants in support of the International Economic Order, the Young Leaders Project, Soviet Russia and Eastern European projects, and education about international affairs, such as language and cultural studies courses. The grant files also contain materials from Travel and Study grants and several grant competitions.
  - American Studies papers - grant supported, 1967-1976 (Box 4)
  - Canadian based institutions - grants, 1969-1976 (Box 4)
  - China - grants, 1968 (Box 4)
  - Common Problems of Advanced Industrial Society, 1976 (Box 4)
  - East Asia, Australia, New Zealand - grants, 1968 (Box 4)
  - Eastern Europe - grants, 1964-1974 (Box 4)
  - English as a Second Language - Queben conference, 1961-1967 (Box 4)
  - English as a Second Language - Hungary, 1961-1967 (Box 4)
  - English as a Second Language - Japan, 1961-1967 (Box 4)
  - English as a Second Language - programs, 1961-1967 (Box 4)
  - Environment - grants, 1971 (Box 4)
  - Europe - grants, 1970-1979 (Box 4)
  - Europe and Canada - list of grants, 1970-1971 (Box 4)
  - Europe and Canada - programs, 1967-1969 (Box 4)
  - France and Germany - grants, 1951-1978 (Box 4)
  - Grantee publications, 1969-1974 (Box 4)
  - Grantee publications - annual reports, 1975-1977 (Box 4)
  - Greece and Italy - grants, 1967-1972 (Box 4)
  - Hungarian Refugee grants, 1957-1963 (Box 4)
  - Internation Affairs programs grants, 1951-1968 (Box 4)
  - International Economic Order - Announcements and grantees, 1972-1977 (Box 4)
  - International Economic Order - Correspondence, 1973-1980 (Box 5)
  - International Economic Order - International correspondence, 1978-1979 (Box 5)
  - International Economic Order - Progress reports, 1974-1976 (Box 5)
  - International Economics - EIA grants, 1963-1981 (Box 5)
  - International Economics - EIA grants, 1970-1981 (Box 5)
  - International Economics - Grantees, 1973-1977 (Box 5)
  - International Law - grants, 1963-1971 (Box 5)
  - International Training and Research grants, 1951-1966 (Box 5)
  - Japan - grants, 1968-1973 (Box 5)
  - List of grants for fiscal year, 1969 (Box 5)
  - List of grants by program categories, 1950-1966 (Box 5)
  - "Noteworthy" grants, 1969 (Box 5)
  - Russian Research competition - Evaluations, 1975 (Box 5)
  - Scandinavia - grants, 1967-1972 (Box 5)
  - Scholars - grants, 1981 (Box 5)
  - Soviet / Eastern Europe Research competition, 1974-1975 (Box 5)
  - Soviet / Eastern Europe Research competition, 1975 (Box 5)
  - Travel and Study grants, 1969 (Box 5)
  - Travel and Study grants, 1964 (Box 5)
  - Travel and Study grants - Awards, 1961-1967 (Box 5)
  - Travel and Study grants - Basic materials, 1965 (Box 5)
  - Travel and Study grants - Europe, 1957-1971 (Box 5)
  - Travel and Study grants - lists of grants, 1957-1973 (Box 5)
  - Two-Keys - Correspondence, 1972-1973 (Box 5)
  - Two-Keys - European grants, 1968-1973 (Box 5)
  - "Umbrella" project proposals, 1965 (Box 5)
  - United Nations - grants, 1968-1972 (Box 5)
  - Women - grants list, 1980 (Box 5)
  - Young Leaders Project - correspondence, 1965-1966 (Box 5)
  - Young Leaders Project - discussion and comments, 1965-1966 (Box 5)
  - Young Leaders Project - Latin America, UK, US, 1965-1966 (Box 6)
  - Young Leaders Project - program layout, 1965-1966 (Box 6)
- Arms Control, 1969-1979; IV
  A key program of the International Affairs Department focused on arms control research. These files contain documents supporting the goals of the arms control program, including setting up academic centers of training and research, an educational program for defense analysts or defense “managers”, and training of arms control specialists from less developed countries. In addition, these records include publications from the US Department of State and the US Arms Control and Disarmament Agency. The arms control program also supported a grant contest for research into arms control issues and solutions. Many of these grants supported conflict study programs in universities such as Harvard and MIT.
  - Appropriations for research, 1973 (Box 6)
  - Articles - PRC Arms Control, France and China, undated (Box 6)
  - Competition - Arms Control - letters to winners and losers, evaluations, 1976 (Box 6)
  - Competition - Arms Control - planning, 1977 (Box 6)
  - Competition - Arms Control - rejected proposals (sample), 1976 (Box 6)
  - Ford Foundation Arms Control activities - documents, 1971-1977 (Box 6)
  - Ford Foundation Arms Control activities - documents, 1972-1974 (Box 6)
  - Ford Foundation concerns with Peace and International Security, 1974 (Box 6)
  - Meeting - Arms Control, 1974 (Box 6)
  - Outside Evaluators - Centers for Research and Training in International Security and Arms Control, 1977-1978 (Box 6)
  - Outside Evaluators - Kaysen Report on the Foundation and Arms Control, 1973 (Box 6)
  - Papers on Arms Control, 1971-1974 (Box 6)
  - Programs in International Security and Arms Control, 1979 (Box 6)
  - Programs in Arms Control and International Security, 1972 (Box 6)
  - SALT (Stategic Arms Limitation Talks) documents, 1969-1973 (Box 6)
  - Seminar - Pittsburgh - Department of State publications, 1978 (Box 6)
  - Seminar - Pittsburgh - Miscellaneous publications, 1978 (Box 6)
  - Seminar - Pittsburgh - US Arms Control and Disarmament Agency publications, 1978 (Box 6)
  - Seminar - US and Japan Defense Relations - NYC, 1979 (Box 6)
  - Seminar - US and Japan Defense Relations - Proposal by Institute of War and Peace Studies, 1979 (Box 6)
- Exchanges, 1954-1970; V
  The International Affairs Department supported scientific and scholarly exchanges with Eastern Europe, including the USSR. The programs include scholarly exchanges in Poland, Yugoslavia, and Rumania. Also supported were an Artists in Residence program in Berlin, funding for Hungarian Student Refugees to study abroad, and scientist exchanges in the USSR and various other countries.
  - Berlin Artists in Residence - General, 1963-1965 (Box 7)
    Related Materials
    See also Ford Foundation grant 06300351 (PA63-351), German Academic Exchange Service, PROVIDE OPPORTUNITIES FOR YOUNG AND RENOWNED CULTURAL AND INTELLECTUAL LEADERS TO WORK AND TO VISIT BERLIN.
    Scope and Contents
    Artist-In-Residence grantees include: Russero Albanese, Carlos Alsina-Roque, Gilbert Amy, Louis Andriessen, Wystan H. Auden, Ingeborg Bachmann, Angelica Behrmann, Enrique Belloc, Frederic Benrath, Eric Bentley, Elaza Benyoetz-Koppel, Luciano Berio, Michel Butor, Elliott Carter, Joel Chadabe, Mario Cravo, Alvin Curran, Franco Di Carlo, Roberto Dionisio, Wojciech Fangor, Ruth Francken-Steinreich, Alberto Ginastera, Vinko Globokar, Marvin Goldstein, Witold Gombrowicz, Dagmar Hader, Werner Haderer, Hans-Werner Henze, Peter Heyworth, Shirley Jaffe, Gerard Koch, Hans Koellreutter, Morcedes Kruschewsky, Klaus Matthes, Rudiger Rufer, Filipe Pires, Joachim Prenzlow, Lucio Raccanelli, Piers P. Read, Antonio Reboucas, Remo Remotti, Klaus Roehler, Frederic Rzewski, Hans-Dietrich Sander, William Scott, Roger Sessions, Gin Stefani, James Sutcliffe, Yuji Takahashi, Emilio Vedova, Roman Vlad, Paul Westheim, Yannis Xenakis, and Isang Yun.
  - Berlin Artists in Residence - Karl Haas, 1963 (Box 7)
  - Bulgarian awards, 1968-1969 (Box 7)
  - Eastern European Programs - Communist controlled countries, 1957-1960 (Box 7)
  - Eastern European Programs - Finances and Appropriations, 1964-1968 (Box 7)
  - Eastern European Programs - General, 1957-1968 (Box 7)
  - Eastern European Programs - Prospects, 1957-1968 (Box 7)
  - Eastern European Programs - Reports, 1965-1968 (Box 7)
  - Eastern European Programs - Selection team candidates, 1964-1967 (Box 7)
  - Eastern European Programs - Statistics, press releases, general information, 1961-1968 (Box 7)
  - Eastern European Programs - Trips to East Europe, 1968 (Box 7)
  - European trips and Conversations - Eugene Staples, 1967 (Box 7)
  - Hungarian Awards and Correspondence, 1966-1969 (Box 7)
  - Hungarian Program, 1965-1966 (Box 7)
  - Hungarian Refugee Students - approprations, 1956-1963 (Box 7)
  - Hungarian Refugee Student program, 1956-1960 (Box 7)
  - Hungary - Reports - Institute of International Education, 1965-1969 (Box 7)
  - Polish Exchange - Application form, selectees, grantees, 1957-1959 (Box 7)
  - Polish Exchange - Background and Guidelines for selection team, 1961 (Box 7)
  - Polish Exchange - Candidates, Awards, Selections, 1963-1970 (Box 7)
  - Polish Exchange - Docket items, 1958 (Box 7)
  - Polish Exchange - General information, 1957-1961 (Box 7)
  - Polish Exchange - Missions, 1957-1959 (Box 7)
  - Polish Exchange - Reports - Institute of International Education, 1967-1968 (Box 7)
  - Polish Exchange - Selection team material - Mr. Stone's folder, 1958-1959 (Box 7)
  - Polish Exchange - Statistics, 1957-1965 (Box 7)
  - Polish Exchange - Statistics and Roundtable, 1957-1969 (Box 7)
  - Rumanian Program - Candidates, 1964-1966 (Box 7)
  - Rumanian Program - General Information, 1963-1965 (Box 7)
  - USSR - Appropriations - scholarly exchange, 1959-1963 (Box 7)
  - USSR - Cultural Exchange, 1959-1960 (Box 7)
  - USSR - Exchange of Scientists agreement, 1959 (Box 7)
  - USSR - General, 1953-1959 (Box 7)
  - Yugoslavian Program - Awardees, 1963-1969 (Box 7)
  - Yugoslavian Program - Background, 1958-1967 (Box 7)
  - Yugoslavian Program - Candidates and selections, 1966-1969 (Box 7)
  - Yugoslavian Program - General information, 1954-1960 (Box 7)
  - Yugoslavian Program - Mission Briefing documents, 1963 (Box 7)
  - Yugoslavian Program - Projects, 1965-1967 (Box 7)
  - Yugoslavian Program - Reports, 1959-1969 (Box 7)
- Conferences, 1954-1978; VI
  Conferences were hosted or sponsored by the International Affairs Department in support of its mission of outreach and education. These records include planning and meeting notes, agendas, programs, correspondence and lists and biographies of participants. The conferences covered various international topics, including European Development and Policy, Higher Education, and Foreign Cultures. Conferences took place in Japan, Versailles, the US, and several other places.
  - Ditchley Park Higher Education Meeting, 1964 (Box 8)
  - Ditchley Park Higher Education Meeting - Transcripts (3 folders), 1964 (Box 8)
  - European and American Foundation Executives Meeting - Villa Serbelloni - Bellagio, 1969 (Box 8)
  - European and American Foundation Executives Meeting - Villa Serbelloni - Bellagio - Correspondence, 1969 (Box 8)
  - European Overseas Development Meeting - Fregene, Italy, 1961 (Box 8)
  - Ford Foundation Europe conference, 1971 (Box 8)
  - International Division Conference - New York, 1973 (Box 8)
  - International Press Institute Meeting at Ford Foundation, 1965 (Box 8)
  - Japanese Conference (first) - Dartmouth College, NH (3 folders), 1962 (Box 8)
  - Japanese Conference (second) - Kurashiki, Japan, 1964 (Box 8)
  - Japanese Conference (third) - Williamsburg, VA - Agenda and schedule, 1967 (Box 8)
  - Japanese Conference (third) - Williamsburg, VA - Participants, American and Japanese, 1967 (Box 8)
  - Japanese Conference (third) - Williamsburg, VA - Roundtable papers, 1967 (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous sponsored conferences, 1954-1967 (Box 8)
  - Policy Studies in Europe - Versailles, 1977-1978 (Box 8)